Guide to the George B. Darling Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George B. Darling papers
1805-1995
MS 770
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
30
(74 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, and writings which document the professional career of George B. Darling. The papers highlight Darling's role as head of the Division of Medicine at Yale University, 1946-1953, and as director of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission, 1957-1972. The papers also include files from Darling's participation in Operation Crossroads as a civilian observer of the atomic testing at Bikini Atoll. There are also photographs from personal travel around the world and papers of various members of the Darling, Smith, and Shaw families. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Darling, George Bapst, 1905-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George B. Darling, 1976-1987, and the estate of George B. Darling, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
George Bapst Darling, the son of George Bapst and Alice Emma Smith Darling, was born in Boston, Massachusetts, on December 30, 1905. He attended Boston English High School and Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts. In 1927, he graduated from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and completed work for his doctorate in public health at the University of Michigan in 1931. He married Ann Flora Shaw on June 24, 1931.
Darling worked as a research associate and assistant epidemiologist for the Detroit Department of Health from 1927 until 1932. He then joined the W. K. Kellogg Foundation as associate executive director and served in successively more responsible positions until he was made president of the foundation in 1940, in which capacity he served until 1943. In that year he moved to Washington, D.C. where he became an expert in the administration of medical and scientific affairs. He served as executive secretary of the Committee on Military Medicine of the National Research Council. From 1944-1945, he also served as its vice-chairman of the Division of Medical Sciences. He became executive secretary of both the National Academy of Sciences and the National Research Council in 1945.
In February 1946, Yale University President Charles Seymour asked Darling to accept a new position at the university as director of medical affairs. Seymour envisioned that the director would be a central university administrative officer, with responsibility for the conduct of all university interests represented in its medical school, school of nursing, department of public health, and hospital. The director would be responsible for the budgets of those units and would sit with the Educational Policy Committee of the Corporation, whenever matters ofmedical education were under consideration. Darling accepted this position, but, before moving to New Haven, he went as a non-military observer of Operation Crossroads to witness the atomic bomb testing being conducted on Bikini Atoll during the summer of 1946.
The post-war years were a time of upheaval and reorganization in medicine and health care delivery in the United States. In his years as director of medical affairs at Yale, Darling was confronted with the high costs of medical education and the possibility that the Medical School might not have the funding to function. He lobbied for federal government funding for research and development of medical facilities. There were also discussions of Yale's role in filling the need for training for Connecticut physicians and the desire of some to establish a medical school at the University of Connecticut. Yale needed to redefine its financial relationship with Grace-New Haven Community Hospital (which would become Yale-New Haven Hospital) and help develop methods to provide medical care for indigent patients. On both issues, he worked and became close friends with the hospital's new executive director Albert Snoke. There was also concern in the medical profession over the ethics of Yale School of Medicine faculty treating patients in the various hospital clinics and collecting fees for their services. During the Korean War, Darling sought ways to balance the need to provide medical personnel for the armed forces without disrupting medical education by drafting faculty and students.
Following the hiring of a new dean of the Medical School and the assumption of the Yale presidency by A. Whitney Griswold, the oversight of medical affairs at Yale was reconfigured. With his position eliminated in 1952, Darling became professor of human ecology, a title he held until his retirement in 1974. Darling, however, only taught unti1 1957. In that year, he took what was intended to be a temporary leave of absence from Yale to become the director of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission (ABCC) in Hiroshima, Japan. Darling served in this capacity until 1972.
The ABCC was a joint undertaking of the National Academy of Sciences and the Japanese Government. It had been collecting data and publishing reports on the health of atomic bomb survivors since 1948. Darling became the chief administrator for a team of Japanese and American scientists carrying out extensive research on how the atomic bomb blasts over Hiroshima and Nagasaki continued to affect the health and life spans of residents. Periodically, the researchers examined radiation bum survivors, and the results ofthese studies shed new light on the behavior of genes and cancer cells.
Darling stressed the importance of harmony and diversity in this undertaking and believed that the cooperation of the local community was an absolute prerequisite to the ABCC program. Reports and other publications of the commission were published in bi-lingual format. During his tenure, there was an increase in mutual assistance and exchange of personnel with Japanese universities and medical institutions. As director, Darling was involved in labor disputes and negotiations over the share of funding to be provided by each ofthe commission's sponsors, as well as efforts to publicize the commission's work. He was often called upon to appear at ceremonial functions and to escort visiting dignitaries. He and his wife Ann became familiar with Japanese customs and life style and were successful in attracting, acclimating, and retaining young American scientists for the commission's work. In order to further this work, Mrs. Darling co-authored a small book on mastering the art ofthe Japanese tea ceremony.
In recognition of his efforts, Darling was honored with the Japan Medical Association's Supreme Award of Golden Orchid in 1967. He received the United States Atomic Energy Commission citation for meritorious contributions to the nation's atomic energy program in 1970. On leaving Japan in 1972, he returned to Washington, D.C. as a scholar in residence at the John E. Fogarty International Center for Advanced Studies in the Health Sciences, which was sponsored by the National Institutes of Health.
The Darlings were masterful at entertaining guests. They enjoyed travel and visited six of the seven continents. A bon vivant, George Darling attended Rotary International meetings wherever he went. In 1968, Darling was named a Paul Harris Fellow ofthe Rotary Foundation of Rotary International in recognition of his contributions to the international program. For several years the Darlings also enjoyed a summer retreat on Cut-in-Two Island, one of the Thimble Islands off-shore from Branford, Connecticut. In retirement, the couple returned to Hamden, Connecticut, where Darling died at age 89, on March 30, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The George Bapst Darling Papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, and writings, which document Darling's service with the W. K. Kellogg Foundation, his role as head of the Division of Medicine at Yale University, 1946-1953, and his extended term as director of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission, 1957-1972. The papers also include files from Darling's participation in Operation Crossroads as a civilian observer of the atomic testing at Bikini Atoll, photographs from personal travel around the world, and papers of various members ofthe Darling, Smith, and Shaw families.
The papers are arranged in six series, but no one series contains all materials relating to a particular phase of Darling's career. In many instances, when material is divided between series cross references in the series listings direct the reader to other relevant material. Series I, General Files, includes materials, predominately correspondence, from all of Darling's adult life, and includes documents relating to both personal and professional matters. Series II, Yale Files, includes those files specifically created while Darling served as head of the Division of Medicine and while teaching at Yale University, while Series III, Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission Files, contains those files Darling retained from his fifteen years in Japan. Nevertheless, correspondence with personal friends and colleagues in Series I may also be of interest to those studying both the Yale years and ABCC assignment. Series IV, Writings, contains manuscripts, printed copies, and speech notes of Darling's authorship, but correspondence with publishers or concerning arrangements for a speech are found in the first three series. Series V includes personal papers of both George and Ann Darling, as well as papers from other members of both their families. Diaries and memorabilia in this series may be of use to those studying the Darlings' years in Japan, as may be the extensive collection of photographs found in Series VI.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. General Files, 1927-1991. II. Yale Files, 1945-1957. III. Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission Files, 1948-1972. IV. Writings, 1920s-1979. V. Family and Personal Papers, 1805-1995. VI. Photographs, 1813-1995.
Human ecology; Medical education -- Finance; Operation Crossroads, Marshall Islands, 1946; Public health -- Study and teaching; Radiation victims; Voyages and travels; Hiroshima-shi (Japan); Japan -- Description and travel; Photographs; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Allen, Leroy; Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Cannan, R. Keith (Robert Keith), 1894-1971; Coombe, Reginald G.; Darling, Ann; Darling, George Bapst, 1905-1995; Dunham, Charles L., 1906-1975; Gardner, Herbert; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Hiscock, Ira V. (Ira Vaughan), 1892-; Lippard, Vernon W., 1905-; Long, C. N. H. (Cyril Norman Hugh), 1901-1970; Pritchard, Stuart; Russell, Walter J.; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Snoke, Albert W. (Albert Waldo), 1907-; Vaughan, Henry F. (Henry Frieze), 1889-1979; Association of American Medical Colleges; Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission; Connecticut State Medical Society; Grace-New Haven Community Hospital; John E. Fogarty International Center for Advanced Study in the Health Sciences; Michigan Community Health Project; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); National Fund for Medical Education (U.S.); National Research Council (U.S.); Rotary Club of Hiroshima; Rotary International; W.K. Kellogg Foundation; Yale University. Department of Epidemiology and Public Health; Yale University. School of Medicine
- General Files, 1927-1991; Series I
  Arrangement
  The papers are arranged in alphabetical order by personal and corporate name.
  Scope and Contents
  The General Files span George Darling's entire professional life and include correspondence and other types of papers, both personal and professional in nature. Many of the correspondents are colleagues and friends in the field of public health.
  This series is the best source for information on George Darling's service to the W. K. Kellogg Foundation, but the materials are not Darling's office files from the period. Folder 198 includes a log of Darling's activities during his first year, 1932-1933, at the foundation but no similar material documents his day to day routine during the remainder of his tenure. Rather, his career is reflected in occasional exchanges with various officials of the foundation, such as W. K. Kellogg, Emory Morris, and Stuart Pritchard, particularly at times when Darling or his correspondents were traveling. Through the W. K. Kellogg Foundation files one can learn about the Michigan Community Health Project, which the foundation sponsored. Of note also is the correspondence with Henry F. Vaughan, who, as commissioner of health for Detroit, worked with the foundation. Vaughan later taught at the University of Michigan's School of Public Health, and he continued to correspond with Darling all throughout his career.
  The foundation was a training center for numerous health engineers and sanitarians, and there are numerous files for those with whom Darling became acquainted during the Kellogg years. These include Morley Beckett, Al Coburn, Bob Coleman, Herbert Dunsmore, Leon Fox, John E. Gordon, Arthur Hewig, Marshall Jennison, Russell Johnson, Fred Kent, Ray Nebelung, and Clair E. Turner. Their letters describe their experiences during World War II and their later careers in Michigan and around the world. John E. Gordon's letters, for instance, record his experiences in Romania. During the 1980s a group of these Kellogg graduates started a newsletter in which they exchanged news of their pursuits. These newsletters are filed in folder 203.
  There is very little in the series, or in the papers, which documents Darling's work for the National Academy of Sciences and the National Research Council in Washington, D.C. Darling's trip to the Pacific to witness Operation Bikini is recorded in letters to his mother Alice Darling and to his wife Ann Shaw Darling.
  This series is not rich in material for Darling's years in New Haven. It contains correspondence with various members of the Yale administration and faculty, but most of these exchanges relate to personal or social matters or date from after the Darlings' departure for Japan. There is a sizeable amount of this latter correspondence with Darling's close friend Albert Snoke. During Darling's years in Japan he hosted many visitors from the United States, including many Yale colleagues. Correspondence with them concerns arrangements for their travels but also includes impressions of their visits. This type of correspondence reflects the hospitality for which the Darlings gained renown. Cross-references in the series listing refer to correspondence between 1946 and 1957 in Series II.
  Similarly, the series does not contain Darling's official correspondence as executive director ofthe Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission. However, in the Series I files for R. Keith Cannan there is a chronological arrangement of both incoming and outgoing correspondence for the years 1957-1960 which is substantive on ABCC matters. Cannan, who was with the National Research Council, received reports from Darling and kept him informed of decisions made in Washington. There is also some correspondence toward the end ofDarling's tenure with his successor Leroy Allen.
  For the most part Darling's associates from ABCC correspond with him only when he is traveling and after his retirement. Kenji Joji, Hiroshi Maki, and Tsutornu (Dutch) Nakayama write of what is happening both in the office and with their family and friends. Hamilton Howard, Seymour Jablon, M. E. Rappaport, and Walter J. Russell, are among the Americans serving with the commission who continue to correspond with Darling after 1972. The United States Atomic Energy files concern arrangements for the citation Darling received.
  From 1946 through 1987, the Darlings sent an annual holiday letter to friends and family. These letters summarize projects, travel, and some personal events. They can be helpful in following a major portion of Darling's professional career and life in retirement.
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, LeRoy and Elsie, 1962-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - American Public Health Association, 1940-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Public Health Association. Committee on Public Health and the Behavioral Sciences, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ba-Bi (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - BI-Bu (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Banks, A. Leslie, 1949-1956, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bar Hunters, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barker, Creighton
    General note
    See: Series II, folder 13
  - Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beckett, Morley, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Beere, David, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Beeson, Paul
    See: Series I1, folders 139-140
  - Belsky, Joseph L., 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Berger, Spencer
    See: Series II, folders 17-22
  - Bishop, Lottie
    See: Series IT, folder 135
  - Blake, Francis
    See: Series I1, folder 131
  - Bronk, Detlev, 1957-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Buck, Carl E., 1943-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Buck, Norman S., 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ca-CI (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Co-Cu (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cannan, R. Keith, 1936, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
  - Colbert, James W.
    See: Series II, folder 120
  - Concannon, Matthias, 1940-1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Coombe, Reginald
    See: Series II, folders 173-182
  - Cosmos Club, 1944-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Council of Teaching Hospitals, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Curtis, Francis J., 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cutting, Windsor, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - D (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Darling, Alice, 1929-1946, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Darling, Ann, 1928-1980 (Box 3, Folder 31~34)
  - Davison, Wilburt C., 1944-1966 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Dejany, Aouney, 1936-1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Detroit. Department of Health, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Dunsmore, Herbert L., 1944-1952 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Dwyer, Hugh
    See: Series II, folders 123-125
  - E (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Elkin, Daniel C.
  - Emerson, Haven, 1940-1950 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - F (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ferrell, John A, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Fleming, Grant, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Fogarty International Center, 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Fogarty Scholars-in-Residence Program
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 46-48)
  - Forbes, Thomas, 1945-1946, 1967-1971, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Fox, Leon, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Fry, Clements C.
    See: Series II, folders 100-102
  - Fulton, John F., 1945 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    See also: Series II, folders 127, 137, 144, 153, 154
  - Furniss, Edgar
    See: Series II, folders 16, 116
  - G (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Gardner, Herbert, 1962-1973 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Gardner, William U.
    See: Series II, folder 136
  - Gelfan, Samuel
    See: Series II, folder 144
  - Gibson, William C., 1944-1961 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Goosens, Ernest, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Gordon, John E., 1933-1950 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Griswold, A Whitney
    See: Series II, folder 115
  - H (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Haggerty, James, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Hamai, Shinzo, 1962-1967 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Hamilton, Howard, 1967-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Handler, Philip, 1969-1974 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Harris, Ben, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Harris, Robert S., 1943-1954 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Harvard University, 1943-1949 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1947, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    See also: Series II, folder 151
  - Hewig, Arthur, 1942-1959 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Hiscock, Ira V., 1956-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 67-68)
    See also: Series II, folders 61-62, 91-97
  - Holden, Reuben M., 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    See also: Series II, folders 173-182
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1936-1943 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Horning, Benjamin, 1944-1947 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Hunter, Robert
  - I (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - J (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Jablon, Seymour, 1973-1985 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - James, Maurice D., 1946-1968 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Japan-America Society of Washington, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Jennison, Marshall [Jenny], 1931, 1960-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Johnson, Kenneth, 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Johnson, Russell, 1945-1969 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Joji, Kenji, 1962-1991 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Ka-Kin (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Kip-Kuw (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Kahn, Eugene
    See: Series II, folder 146
  - Kellogg, W. K., 1934-1946 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Kent, Frederick S., 1942-1965 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Kinde, Matthew R., 1940-1975 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Kirkpatrick, Sidney D., 1946 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Kraft, Annette and Charles, 1966-1977 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - L (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Ladies Aid, 1946-1953 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Lee, Chong-Hak, 1956-1968 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Lee, Richard K. C., 1964-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Lindskog, Gustaf
    See: Series II, folder 151
  - Lippard, Vernon, 1958-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 93)
    See also: Series II, folder 134
  - Long, C. N. H., 1952, 1964-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 94)
    See also: Series II, folder 132-133
  - Ma-Me (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Mi-Mu (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Maki, Hiroshi, 1957-1985 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Massachusettes Institute of Technology. Visiting Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - McMahon, Brien, 1948-1950 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - McRae, Vada, 1942-1944 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Meid, Don, 1946-1967 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Meigs, J. Wister, 1949-1973 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund, 1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Miller, Robert W., 1957-1976 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Montgomery, Mildred, 1941-1973 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Morito, Tatsuo, 1957-1970 (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Morris, Emory, 1936-1974 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Murdock, Thomas
    See: Series II, folders 14, 173-182
  - Na (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Ne-Nu (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Nagai, Isamu, 1962-1973 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Nagano, Itsui, 1963-1973 (Box 8, Folder 111)
  - Nkaidzunmi, Masanori, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Nakamura, Keizo, 1969-1981 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Nakayama, Tsutomu [Dutch], 1961-1984 (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1944-1975 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - National Conference on Aging, 1950-1951, undated
  - National Institutes of Health. Gerontology Research Center Seminar, 1973-1974, undated
    See also: Folders 44-48
  - National Research Council (D. S.), 1941-1970 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Nebelung, Ray, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Nisimaru, Yasuyosi, 1962-1981 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - O (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Ohara, Hiroo, 1958-1962 (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Pa (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Pe-Pi (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Po-Pu (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - Pany, Robert, 1946-1970 (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - Paul, John Rodman
    See: Series II, folder 145
  - Peters, John
    See: Series II, folders 119, 139-140
  - Pond, M. Allen
  - Pritchard, Myra Helmer, 1941-1943 (Box 9, Folder 129)
  - Pritchard, Stuart, 1932-1940 (Box 9, Folder 130-131)
  - R (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - Radiation Effects Research Foundation, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - Rappaport, Michael [Mick], 1958-1975 (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - Redlich, Fredrick C., 1952-1972 (Box 9, Folder 135)
    See also: Series II, folders 146-149
  - Robbins, Hugh B., 1944-1984 (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - Robinson, Borday
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1946-1952 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Roemer, Milton, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 138)
    See also: Series II, folders 91-97
  - Rogers, Orville F.
    See: Series II, folder 99
  - Rotary Club of Hiroshima, 1964-1971 (Box 9, Folder 139-140)
  - Roth, Armin, 1945-1949 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Russell, Walter J., 1966-1981, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 142-143)
  - Sa-Se (Box 10, Folder 144)
  - Sh-So (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Sp-St (Box 10, Folder 146)